你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎回到pwn学院
welcome back to pwn College
我们谈论的是高级漏洞利用
we're talking about advanced exploitation
Linux内核中的竞争条件
specifically race conditions in the Linux kernel
我们为什么要谈这个
why are we talking about this
因为Linux内核中会发生竞争条件
well because race conditions happen in the Linux kernel
内核是隐式并发的
the kernel is implicitly concurrent
如果你有一个内核入口点
if you have a kernel entry point
系统调用
the system call
包括很常见的
including very common one
像ioctl是这些问题的常见来源
ioctl is a common source of these issues
文件访问
a file access
假设你编写了一个在内核中运行的文件系统驱动程序
let's say you've written a file system driver that runs in the kernel
任何类型的中断处理程序
any sort of interrupt handlers
如果你在做一些疯狂的事情
if you're doing something really crazy
所有这些都可以由用户空间同时触发
all of this stuff can be triggered by user space simultaneously concurrently
通过不同的用户空间进程
by many different user space processes
同时运行并与这些内核资源交互
running and interacting with these kernel resources all at once
因此，编写内核代码必须考虑并发性
so kernel code must be written with concurrency in mind
当然，经常没考虑到
and of course often times it is not
哎呦
whoops
我们来看一看
let's take a look
露底了
that shouldn't
那是一个预览
that was a preview of things to come
我们来看看
let's take a look at
内核代码中没考虑并发性，会发生什么
what happens when kernel code is not written with concurrency in mind
这是竞争条件模块题目
here we have a version of one of your race condition challenges
为内核编写的版本
but written for the kernel
有一个ioctl
we have an ioctl
内核驱动程序注册了/proc/pwn-college-ioctl
the kernel driver registers /proc/pwn-college-ioctl
定义了4个ioctl_number
it has 4 ioctl numbers
LOGIN，会将你的权限级别设置为1
and it has LOGIN which sets your privilege level to 1
ADMIN，将其设置为2
ADMIN which sets it to 2
但前提是你已经知道flag了
but only if you already know the flag
它是ADMIN的密码
that is the password for administrative access
SUDO
如果你的访问权限大于1
which once you have administrative access of greater than 1
就将你的ruid、euid等设置为0
sets your real effective and so forth user ids to 0
这正是内核漏洞利用程序会做的事情
this is exactly what a kernel exploit would do
LOGOUT会降低你的权限级别
and a LOGOUT which decrements your privilege level
这基本上是一个疯狂的内核模块版的sudo
this is basically a kernel module sudo in some crazy way
非常粗糙的版本
very hacked up version
当然，问题在于特权级别是一个全局变量
the problem of course is the privilege level is a global variable
这个内核模块做出如下假设
this kernel module makes the Assumption that
一次只有一个线程访问它
only one thread will be accessing it at one time
但事实并非如此
but that is definitely not the case
内核资源可以并发访问
kernel resources can be accessed concurrently
当然，这里的攻击类似于babyrace
of course the attack here is similar as babyrace
权限降低这里
this decrement
如果我们能安排这样一个竞争
if we can set up a race
我们传入LOGIN，特权级别设为1
where we pass privilege level of 1
因为我们不知道flag
we obviously don't know the flag
所以特权级别不能设为2
so we can't make privilege level be 2
如果我们通过了，特权级别是否设置的检查
if we pass the check that checks for privilege level being set
并且
and
同时有两个线程执行到这里
if we get here concurrently with two threads at the same time
或者是同时两个进程执行到这里
or two processes at the same time
都执行PWN_LOGOUT
doing the PWN_LOGOUT ioctl number
都会降低一次特权级别
they will each decrement
最后特权级别将是-1
and we will end up with a privileged level of negative 1
这是一个无符号整型
this is an unsigned INT
正因如此
so because of that
这里的检查就能通过了
this check will now pass
因为特权级别将是40亿多
privilege level will be 4 billion something
满足大于1
which is greater than one
我们将成为root
and we will become root
所以我制造了一个攻击程序
so I created an attack
我们可以用它来探索这个概念
that we can use to explore this concept
很简单
very simple
先启动几个竞争进程
spin off first
这些其实毫无意义
this is actually pointless
这是之前沙盒逃逸视频遗留的
that was a leftover from a previous sandbox thing
首先我们启动4个工作进程
first we spin up four workers
我们在每个工作进程做不同的事情
and in each worker we do a different thing
或者一个进程LOGIN
or in one worker we do the login
这要用密码登录
this will log in with password secret
它可从内核模块中获得
which is from the kernel module
它必须是保密的
that has to be secret
顺便说一下，这是非常不安全的内核编程方法
this by the way is very very unsafe kernel programming practices
永远不要直接访问用户空间
you should never access user space directly
这是用户空间
and this is user space
我应该先从用户空间复制过来
I should have copied it from user
再访问它
and then accessed it
但我想要一个简洁的例子
but I wanted it concise example
我们有一个线程一直在登录
so we have one thread that's always logging in
我们有一个线程
we have one thread that's
哦，我们有三个线程一直登出
oh we have three threads that are always logging out right
思路是
the idea of course we want to
我们想让两个不同线程
hit with two different threads at the same time in here
使特权级减2次
to decrement that twice
然后我的主线程就等着变成root线程
and then my main thread is just waiting to become root
与此同时
and in the meantime
它会一遍遍地尝试SUDO
it is hitting that sudo ioctl over and over and over
一旦竞争成功，它就会关闭所有工作进程，并启动一个shell
once I win it kills the workers and executes a shell
这里不需要-p
and of course I don't need -p here
因为这会将ruid、euid和saved uid都设为零
because this sets the real effective and saved user ids all to zero
所以shell很满意
so shell is perfectly happy
/bin/sh欣然接受了自己是root的这一情况
/bin/sh perfectly happy being root
我们来编译一下
let's compile that
启动内核
launch the kernel
加载模块
load up the module
然后
and
切换到CTF用户
become the ctf user
我们开始攻击吧
and let's do this
真快
that was fast
我们是root了
and we are root
我想指出一点
one thing I want to point out
要强调的是，我们需要执行两次LOGOUT
to stress that we need to hit the logout twice
所以LOGOUT这里
so this logout
我们需要两个进程同时进入
we need to get in here with two process at the same time
如果只有一个进程执行登录
if you just have one process that does the login
一个进程执行登出
one process that does the logout
这永远不会成功
this will never succeed
希望我没说错
I hope this doesn't make me a liar
哦，我不需要重启它
oh I didn't need to restart that
好了，开始吧
okay here we go
开始
here we go
它永远不会结束
no luck and it will never finish
因为已经不在竞争了
because of course we are no longer racing
我们需要2个登出行动，同时在这里执行
we need to race 2 logout actions into here at the same time
这是我们讨论过的一个很标准的竞争条件
so that's a pretty standard race condition that we've explored
这在内核中经常发生
and it happens a lot in the kernel
尽管内核有
this is despite the fact that the kernel of course has
什么来着
what are they called
防止这种情况发生的机制
mechanisms  for preventing this
内核有互斥信号量
the kernel has mutexas semaphores
专门的信号量
specialized semaphores
为快速访问而设计的
made for very fast access of like
该机制允许多个线程可以读取一个共用值
where multiple threads can read a value
但一次只有一个线程可以修改它
and one thread can write it
有通用互斥信号量
there's generic mutex semaphore
等好东西
all sorts of good stuff
通用互斥接口是最简单的
the generic mutex interface is the simplest
其实它非常简单
it's actually super simple
它几乎与pthread互斥锁接口完全相同
it's almost exactly like the pthread mutex interface
你只要在某地声明一个锁
you declare it somewhere
然后就可以加锁，解锁
and then you lock unlock
超级简单
super simple
但不容易理解的是
but it is not easy to understand
什么资源可以被不同线程影响
what resources can be impacted by different threads
特别是在复杂的代码中
especially in complex code
从有大量这类错误的事实，就能看出
and we can see this from the fact that errors persist a lot
我改一下幻灯片
let me fix this slide one second
有大量这类错误
errors persist a lot
就在今年
just this year
在各种内核，不光是linux内核，曝出了20个CVE
there have been 20 CVEs in various kernels not just in linux kernel
都是竞争条件类的
that are specific to race conditions
2017年
in 2017
自动检测这些错误的尝试
kind of the attempt to automatically detect these sort of errors
已经开始了
has started up
传统上，这些错误是手动识别的
traditionally these errors were identified manally
这样做很痛苦
and it is a pain to do so
至少可以这么说
to say the least it's
在我们看的例子中
in the example that we looked at
很明显就能看出
it was very obvious
这里存在竞争条件和对全局变量的不安全访问
where there was a race condition and unsafe access of a global variable
但这在Linux内核这个复杂代码中经常发生
but these happen in complex code in the Linux kernel all the time
Dr. Checker发表于2017年
Dr Checker published in 2017
找到了63个和这个完全一样的竞争条件
found 63 race conditions exactly like this
都是，在不同Android版本中，对全局变量的不安全访问
unsafe access of global variables in different versions of Android
这当然是Linux内核
which of course is Linux kernel
2019年，谷歌发布了 内核并发消毒程序
in 2019 Google released the Kernel concurrency Sanitizer
发现了数百个
that found hundreds
我看到的数字是，发现了多达300个竞争条件在linux内核中
I see numbers as much as 300 of races in the Linux kernel
在2019年和2020年，有更多的学术工作
and in 2019 and 2020 there have been more academic work
创建了识别内核中竞争条件的技术
works that have created techniques to identify race conditions in the kernel
在文件系统，设备驱动程序和各种东西中的竞争条件
in file systems in device drivers and all sorts of things
我特意把这4个写在上面的原因是
the reason I have these 4 specifically up here
它们都是开源的
they're all open source
你可以获取Dr.Checker
you can actually grab Doctor Checker
KCSAN
grab KCSAN
据我所知，KCSAN已经合到Linux内核主线了
actually KCSAN is as far as I am aware merged into the Linux kernel mainline source
你可以玩一下它
so you can actually play around with it
构建一个自己的fuzzer，尝试触发竞争条件
and build your own fuzzers and try to trigger race conditions
我应该提一下
I should mention
这个KCSAN专门用于检测竞争条件
this KCSAN specifically is for detecting the race conditions
Dr Checker是针对静态ELF的工具
Dr Checker is a static ELF tool
并不运行Linux内核
doesn't actually run the Linux kernel
就看看源码
just looks at the source code
这些技术结合了
and then these techniques combine
触发系统调用本身，与静态分析
triggering of system calls themselves with an analysis
来识别何时遇到竞争条件
to identify when race conditions are hit
结论是
the takeaway of course is that
这仍然是一个大问题
this is still a major problem
这四种技术代表
these four techniques represent
仅在Linux内核中就有成百上千的竞争条件
hundreds and hundreds of race conditions found in the Linux kernel alone
还只是过去的三年
in the last three years
或者说过去四年，算上2017年的话
or the last four years I guess if you include 2017
我们仍然
and we're still
这种情况仍在发生
this is still happening
2017年确实是内核竞争条件曝出数量的一个高点
2017 was really was a high point in race conditions in the kernel
但在过去几年里
but over the last couple of years
也在持续稳定地发现竞争条件
there have been very stable amount of race conditions found
所以这告诉我们，还有很多有待发现
so which tells me that there's a lot left to find
当然
of course
在你的练习题中，你会发现一些
in your challenge problems you'll find some
但也许有一天你也会在现实世界中找到一些
but maybe you'll find some in the real world one day as well
祝你好运
good luck